Hi everyone, welcome to this week's Azure update.
It's the 6th of February.
A nice selection of updates this week so you can jump to any particular one you care about the most.
New videos this week, so I thought it was about time to update my kind of state of the Union on Azure, mainly focusing around kind of the identity, the governance and then some of the core compute type capabilities just to bring it up to date.
And then I've seen this over and over again, so.
I gave my Viewpoint on if you should learn AI as a C level executive through to an individual contributor what's the pros what's the cons and obviously my Viewpoint uh too long didn't read is yes you should do I think it is going to be very real it is real today and I think
Those that don't focus today are going to get left behind and there's an acceleration of this learning and you want to be on the right end of that.
So on the compute side.
So one of the things that's changing here is the Azure Monitor agent.
There was a preview feature and it could collect data from virtual machines and send it to a storage account or an event hub.
Now that is being retired.
Now if you were previously sending it to storage for like a low cost option,
One of the things you could use instead is use a custom tabling log analytics using the auxiliary plan.
That's the very low cost tier.
If you're using event hubs, probably being used to then send to some other final destination or product, well, there's actually a lot of increase in what's natively supported.
So you go ahead and look at that as an option as well.
So Azure Kubernetes Fleet Manager now has a namespace scoped placement capabilities.
Remember,
The Kubernetes Fleet Manager is all about at-scale management of AKS clusters, but also Arc-enabled Kubernetes clusters.
So any CNCF compatible Kubernetes deployment.
And what you can do with that Fleet Manager is workload placement, node image, Kubernetes updates, managed namespaces, DNS load balancing.
Now what this now lets me do is instead of focusing a deployment at the cluster and maybe impacting the entire namespace,
With A namespace scoped resource being deployed across multiple clusters, I have more granular control across the specific resources within the namespace I want to update.
For example, I can target based on the resource name, its type, its label, which is going to be really useful if I have a scenario that I have many workloads sharing a single namespace.
So a whole namespace level targeting would be an issue.
So this is a really nice capability for that.
The AMD v6 confidential VMs are now available in new regions.
Remember, the whole point is we have concepts of data encrypted at rest.
We have encryption in transit using things like TLS.
This is...
encrypted in use.
So both the memory and the CPU and the AMD SKUs focus on that whole VM encryption.
So I don't have to make any changes to my application.
I just get that whole VM encryption of the compute and the memory.
So they've added 11 new regions and existing to the existing six.
So it's got a super wide coverage now.
On the networking side.
So App Gateway now has a DRS 2.2 rule set in GA.
So App Gateway is the regional Layer 7 solution.
And when you talk about this DRS rule set, this is the superset of the OWASP core rule set.
I think this is 334, but we add our own sets of Microsoft Threat Intelligence rules to expand the coverage.
Now,
The core rule set 334 had its own new protections, its new detections, but basically we add on top of that additional ones.
And it now has a paranoia level.
So you can set your level of paranoia to try and avoid blocking any legitimate traffic.
And also, App Gateway V2 has an X4ed4 rate limiting in preview.
So the X4ed4, what it does is it shows you the original client's IP, not
just, hey, if there's, for example, a proxy in between it or content delivery network, you would see the IP of the proxy or content delivery network.
So x44 in the header shows me the original client's IP address.
So what I could now do is I could group the data based on that originating client IP, which could be, hey, for the specific IP, but also maybe it's geolocation to help me mitigate any kind of high volume traffic.
Azure Front Door and the Azure Content Delivery Network are retiring the weak cipher suites beginning of April.
So when you use TLS, it's actually a number of different cipher suites for different purposes.
How I'm going to share keys, how I'm going to validate identity, how to actually do symmetric encryption, decryption, how to validate integrity, how I want to hash things.
And as part of those cipher suites, some are weaker than others.
So what these are doing is they're dropping a number of those weak cipher suites, specifically the DHE, the Diffie-Hellman ephemeral ones, which honestly are typically not used today.
Instead, we use the elliptic curve versions of the DHE, which use smaller keys for the same equivalent security level, which means they're faster, they use less resource.
Now, you may not need to do anything.
The specific cipher suites are negotiated on connection, say, hey, I support these ones.
You tell me which ones you support.
We'll negotiate and use the highest, the best ones that we both support.
But if you had, for example, origins behind that gateway that only supported DHE, so AFD and CDN, then you're going to need to make some changes there.
So just keep that in mind.
And then this new virtual network routing appliance is available in preview.
So today, if we wanted to manage how things route, we might use a VM solution in our hub spoke networks that we use a user-defined route to make that the next hop.
And then it goes and forwards stuff on.
But it's a VM.
So that VM can become a bottleneck.
And so what this is, this is a native Azure resource.
It runs in its own dedicated subnet in your VNet.
and it's super high performance, it will horizontally scale, gives you therefore very fast east-west.
So it's i.e.
things within the VNets and connected to the VNets.
Initially it's IPv4 only, but this is now available for you to try it out in preview.
On the storage side, so the Azure Container Storage V2.1 is now GA.
So, Azure Container Storage is designed specifically to provide storage for Kubernetes environments.
Now, normally, and I've done a whole set of videos on this, Kubernetes will typically use container storage interface (CSI) drivers for access to various types of storage that those container workloads can leverage.
Now, those CSI drivers are great, they work across different hyperscalers, they provide a consistent interface experience for developers.
But what this allowed me to do is the AC store, which is what this leverage is, I can use more advanced backend storage options compared to those that back the CSI drivers.
Specifically in the V2, it was around ephemeral disks, either local storage and the AKS nodes, and they talked about what was going to come, Azure Elastic SAN, but it wasn't there initially.
So now the elastic SAN usage is GA.
So that's going to enable you to have very high throughput, reduced management, where I want a stateful workload.
So obviously the ephemeral disk was not stateful.
It was using local storage on the nodes.
Now I can actually use elastic SAN with this.
There's also a new modular installation.
So if I think about the parts that make this work, it will only install the parts I need depending on the options I'm picking.
So it's going to have a reduced cluster footprint.
Azure NetApp Files now has Elastic ZRS as a service in preview.
So obviously the whole point of Zone Redundant is it gives you resiliency and zero data loss in the event of an AZ outage.
Now it's all got the same features of regular ANF service levels, NFSP3, NFSP41, SMB snapshots, encryption, blah, blah, blah, blah.
But it's going to use multiple availability zones.
It's just going to do that behind the scenes.
So
One of the nice things I get here is not only synchronous, because it's within a region, I can do synchronous so I don't lose any data in an unplanned outage of an AZ, but it also is going to give you automatic transparent failover if there is an AZ problem.
On the database side, so serverless workspaces in Azure Databricks are GA.
So as the name suggests, it's serverless.
I can spin up these things as needed.
and only pay for the compute usage I actually need.
Now, you get a certain amount of default storage, so it gives you a very nice SaaS experience for Databricks.
It will be useful when I just do have some serverless production requirement, but also if I'm doing testing or training and they're short-lived, this will be a really good thing to use as well.
It still uses the Unity catalog, so I've still got centralized governance and metadata, so I just don't have to worry about the infrastructure anymore.
Then miscellaneous.
So the Claude Opus 46 is available in Foundry and Copilot Studio.
And I think also it was coming to GitHub Copilot.
So this is Anthropic's most advanced reasoning model.
think very complex coding, think knowledge work and much more.
I think it has a million token context window in beta.
I think it's 128,000 tokens output, but it really is optimized for those very long-running tasks, those very large code bases, very advanced reasoning capabilities.
So that is now available.
And that was it.
As always, I hope that was useful.
Add to my next video.
Take care.